S.MARIMUTHU

+91-7200244433

muthu.sp2512@gmail.com

A Manager with extensive experience in a variety of manufacturing and production fields. Demonstrated ability to assist in not only meeting the organization's objectives, but allowing it to grow as well as reducing costs by using excellent analytical, interpersonal, leadership and organizational skills.

Experience

Production In-charge 10/2022 to Present

Kundan Pipes & Fittings Extrution & Injection Moulding – Coimbatore

Products: PVC, CPVC, UPVC Pipes & Fittings And HDPE Pipes

• Process Optimization:

Involves the methodical approach to reduce the cycle time of the product and to increase the lifetime of the product.

Trial

Looking after development activities of new projects through new mold /material tryouts and using POKE YOKE on require functional areas.

• Trouble shooting:

Involves Identification of the problematic area in mould as well as machine and component and taking suitable remedies of the problem.

- Analyzing the delays/back logs in Operation and Maintenance as well as identifies root-causes behind the downtime.
- Prepare road map and action plan to correct and eliminate theRoot causes, Monitoring & Analysis of Cost of product.
- Training and development of subordinates, workforce.
- Plan & execution of Production activities
 Maintaining ISO documentation and assuring QMS, & EnMS
- Implementation and monitoring in the department.
- Manpower resources allocation & utilization.

Highlight

- Effective
 Communication skill with all levels of Management & Capable to handle a team of 100 peoples
- Good learner and selfmotivated with positive attitudε
- Easily adaptable nature & Leadership Quality
- Enthusiastic to learn new concepts/practices

Education

BE in Mechanical Engineering SCSVMV University with 83%

07/2011 - 12/2014.

Diploma in Mechanical Engineering Govt. Polytechnic College with 89%

07/2005 - 05/2008,

Software exposure & skills

System Software: MS Office 2016 (Word, Excel, PowerPoint), EIP (Enterprise Information Portal), Six sigma, 5S,FMEA, EnMS auditor

Achievements:

- Increased the productivity by reducing the cycle times for all the products.
- Minimized the rejection rates by using the process optimization techniques.
- Reduce the product change time by adopting the systems of KAIZEN and POKAYOKE.

Certifications:

- Certified "Six Sigma Green Belt" Holder from Henry Harvin Education
- Certified "QMS Internal Auditor" for ISO 9001:2015

Experience

Asst. Manager Production. 07/2018 to 10/2022 Larsen & Toubro Ltd., TLT Kanchipuram & Pithampur

Products: Galvanized Material Tower Parts Manufacturing

- Leading a team of eight engineers to deliver the production against the supply plan in line with the client requirement through vendors, sub-contractors, and in-house production.
- Increased productivity of manufacturing operations by 20% by removing wastes in process like waiting time, repetition, excess inventory.
- Developed new vendors for matching components by assessing their machines capacity with requirement, which helped in completion of lots/projects in stipulated time frame.
- Lead a team on ISO system compliance likes Safety, Quality, Environment & Energy management system.
- Reduced consumable cost by 10% by analyzing trends, 80-20 usage concept, production-consumable linkage and by micro monitoring.
- Reduction in level of in-process rework/rejection by 20% using analytical tools like 5-why analysis, cause-effect diagram and Pareto chart to identify root cause and corrective action. Cost optimization by adopting digital initiatives like installation of I.O.T. (internet of things) to monitor live machine performance, online programing for CNC machines to increase productivity & minimize manual error and standardizing the processes by maintaining quality assurance.
- Drive & developed kaizen culture from top to bottom by arranging kaizen competition, for continues improvement in the areas of delivery, quality & safety.
- Streamlined activities pertaining to client inspections like corelation of used raw material against the clearance given by client, helped in maintain trust withclient.

Highlight

- Vendor / Sub Contractor Management
- Cost Optimization
- Vendor Audits
- FMEA
- Inventory Control
- Lean Manufacturing
- Cross Functional Communication
- Product Development
- Kaizen
- Supplier Quality Assurance
- QMS
- Six Sigma
- SPC
- 5S
- Internal ISO Auditor
- 7 QC Tools
- Shop Drawing Development
- Resource Management

Achievements:

- Reduced Supplier PPM 4500 to 1000PPM by implement through Fish bone diagram.
- Reduced In-Process PPM 2000 to 250PPM by implement through Fish bone diagram.
- The cost of fabrication has reduced from Rs.4500/MT to Rs.4150/MT at the Monthly average capacity of 4500MT plant. Period: 2020 to 2022.
- Improve the production capacity of the plant from 130 MT to 180 MT by implement the SPC and FMEA Quality tools(i.e.: Six sigma) in the operation. Period: 2018 to 2019
- Achieved the percentage of zinc consumption less than the target by implementing the process control methods. Period: 2020 to 2021.